[
  {
    "question": "What does a bypass ratio of 11:1 mean?",
    "answer": "For every 1kg of air passing through the combustion chamber, 11kg of air pass bypass the combustion chamber.",
    "id": "526528f2-350c-4d00-8eef-03d752857c18"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a wing tip?",
    "answer": "A wing tip is the part of the wing that is the most distant from the fuselage of a fixed-wing aircraft.",
    "id": "7ba0ceb2-a85b-4e62-93de-9501f69a5eec"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is N1, N2, EGT and EPR?",
    "answer": "N1= Low pressure compressor spool or fan rotation speed. Usually expressed as a % of Max N1.\n\nN2= High pressure compressor rotation speed.\n\nEGT= Exhaust gas temperature, indicates the temperature at the first stage of the turbine, which is the most critical temperature in the engine.\n\nEPR= Engine pressure ratio of the inlet to the jet pipe, displayed on the EPR gauge to use as a parameter for setting engine thrust",
    "id": "78fea1b0-7b51-450e-b838-ec9f34715f2a"
  },
  {
    "question": "While climbing with a SEP, in what temperature range can carb icing occur?",
    "answer": "Carb icing can occur with temperatures as high 30°C and humidity as low as 50%, but it is more likely when below 20°C and high humidity, especially during low power settings.",
    "id": "494de652-23df-4d16-aef7-81fb982789ec"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you load an aircraft for max range?",
    "answer": "The position of the CG directly influences the fuel consumption of an aircraft. An aft position of the CG makes the aircraft less stable, requiring less lift to be generated in both the horizontal stabilizer and wings, reducing the overall drag of the aircraft, and increasing the max range.\n\nYou want to load the the aircraft so that the CG is at, or as close as possible, to the aft limit (Without exceeding it).",
    "id": "537a4fcc-1444-4286-9718-25408b311776"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the benefits of a free turbine?",
    "answer": "A free turbine is a turbine that is not directly connected to the compressor. This allows the compressor to rotate at a different speed than the turbine. Since the turbine speed is coupled with the propeller, this allows for the propeller to be maintained at a constant ideal speed.\n\nAnother advantage is that free turbine engines can be designed to be more compact than their single shaft counterparts",
    "id": "619dbf3a-44f4-43e3-b870-f2c6f3a0b116"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you get out of a spiral dive on a Cessna?",
    "answer": "1. **Unload.** Make sure you are no longer 'pulling G's'\n\n2. **Roll wings level**\n\n3. **Power** Reduce the power to avoid overspeeding.\n\n4. gently pull back on the control wheel to ease out of the dive.\n\nWhen slowed down to a safe airspeed apply throttle as needed.\n\n(N.b.: Do not confuse a spiral dive with a spin)",
    "id": "00257701-0b12-42c1-aeff-4dcd02220e74"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of fuel injection vs a carburetor?",
    "answer": "Fuel injection provides:\n\n - Fuel free from vaporization ice\n\n- Better economy through metered delivery\n- More responsive and efficient engine\n\n- Less maintenance",
    "id": "520400ef-070e-4a60-be66-39f1cb25a710"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does the wing stall first on a typical SEP Aircraft (Cessna, Tecnam, ...)?",
    "answer": "At the wing root. This is a property of rectangular wings, but it's also common to find close to the wing root devices that make it so that the wing root stalls first.",
    "id": "bc1afadd-c2ad-4f81-ad15-703c28ec6dd9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are swept wings effective?",
    "answer": "Swept wings are designed to be the most effective at high speeds. At low speeds, a swept wing produces less lift than its straight counterpart.",
    "id": "60800d6b-ce85-4579-9f2e-7470fe70f3f3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you prevent an aircraft reaching Mcrit?",
    "answer": "Decreasing speed, by reducing engine power or pitching up.",
    "id": "a1b182ef-72e3-4ff8-96b9-83e0f11dbe55"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why don’t you use carburetor heat on the ground for long periods?",
    "answer": "Battery power to the starter motors.",
    "id": "d5ba8914-a4ba-4bb7-8247-4e1b46b7b203"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does GPWS work?",
    "answer": "GPWS is a central computer system that receives various data inputs on configuration, (radio altimeter) height/altitude and instrument landing system glide slope deviation and is able to alert the pilot when a dangerous situation is about to occur.",
    "id": "7999daa3-5113-4df6-95b5-c0e64702a5e3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the speed of sound at sea level according to ISA?",
    "answer": "662 kts\n\nLocal speed of sound = 39 x √(Temperature in Kelvin)\n\n15°C in Kelvin is (15 + 273) = 288\n\nSo the local speed of sound = 39 x √288 = 662 kts",
    "id": "7502a91d-d751-403a-85ee-3def9f803ebf"
  },
  {
    "question": "If in a go-around, which take-off stages will still apply?",
    "answer": "None. The go around procedure is distinct from the take off procedure. You will still have an acceleration altitude, but you will not have a screen height, V1, Vr, V2, flap retraction altitude, etc.",
    "id": "aa1c4108-a14e-4a5b-887e-e4f7302df48d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is a great circle the shortest distance between two points?",
    "answer": "The track changes constantly.",
    "id": "f40b9f5f-9d6b-4052-afdf-17173519fb54"
  },
  {
    "question": "What errors would cause an altimeter to malfunction?",
    "answer": "Altimeter errors:\n\nInstrument error\nPressure error\nTime-lag error\nBarometric error",
    "id": "69eb8f4d-3ea5-4390-9085-910df2ecd28f"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is induced drag?",
    "answer": "Induced drag and its wing tip vortices are a direct consequence of the creation of lift by the wing.\n\nSince the Coefficient of Lift is large when the Angle of Attack is large, induced drag is inversely proportional to the square of the speed whereas all other drag is directly proportional to the square of the speed.\n\nThe effect of this is that induced drag is relatively unimportant at high speed in the cruise and descent where it probably represents less than 10% of total drag. In the climb, it is more important representing at least 20% of total drag. At slow speeds just after take off and in the initial climb, it is of maximum importance and may produce as much as 70% of total drag.\n\nFinally, when looking at the potential strength of wing tip vortices, all this theory on induced drag must be moderated by the effect of aircraft weight. Induced drag will always increase with aircraft weight.",
    "id": "09e4bff4-09b4-4f97-bb29-a9ca760a64b5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of swept wings?",
    "answer": "Swept wings are:\n\nBetter for high speed flight as they have minimal camber and thickness reduce drag and delay Mcrit\nMore stable in turbulence as they produce less lift and as a result they are less responsive to updraughts",
    "id": "bd38c8cd-0826-45a9-bf2a-f72069176c0b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is tire creep, and is it important?",
    "answer": "Tire creep is the tendency of the tire to rotate slowly around the wheel hub as a result of a millisecond landing friction on the tire before wheel spin occurs.\n\nYes, it is important because if there is too much creep the tire can tear out the inflation valve and cause the tire to burst.",
    "id": "23b807ac-78e4-4b5e-88bb-359e94f5384b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of a locator?",
    "answer": "To notify the crew of the aircraft of a particular position on the IAP.\n\nLocators have been largely replaced with Distance Measuring Equipment (DME), but they can sometimes be found associated with Outer or Middle Markers where they are referred to as Locator Outer Marker (LOM) or Locator Middle Marker (LMM).",
    "id": "01d4436f-3034-40ef-ae2d-ae38843f9f94"
  },
  {
    "question": "How much thrust comes from the N1 fan?",
    "answer": "Depends on the engine.\n\nIn the case of the 737-800 CFM56, 27,300lbs total thrust at a ratio of 5.5:1",
    "id": "4c3e9de5-3aa1-419e-9634-7efe8afc48ff"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you calculate Vref?",
    "answer": "Vref = 1.3 x Vs0 (stall speed in the landing configuration).",
    "id": "b572f8f9-25d2-40a1-bb23-619a82dbeaa7"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are outside the range of any VOR’s/NDB's, how does the aircraft know where it is?",
    "answer": "Via INS/IRS/GPS",
    "id": "bbd48b34-89a9-4e22-af7f-07e5ec5f9eb4"
  },

  {
    "question": "How does an altimeter work and which errors can an altimeter experience?",
    "answer": "When an aircraft climbs, the static pressure in the instrument case decreases, which allows the enclosed capsule to expand.\n\nThis in turn moves the needle on the instrument to indicate a corresponding altitude.\n\nDuring descent, the opposite function applies.\n\nAltimeter errors can originate and vary from:\n\nInstrument\nPressure\nTime-lag\nBarometric\nDensity\nTemperature\nBlocked static port",
    "id": "4eb39618-9286-4d88-9f06-4adf07332272"
  },
  {
    "question": "You need to uplift four tonnes of fuel, how many litres would you ask for if the SG is 0.8?",
    "answer": "5000 litres\n\n(4 tonnes / 0.8 = 5000 litters)",
    "id": "5e2fb8da-3490-4af1-9685-15eb826c16b8"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is BEM?",
    "answer": "Basic Empty Mass (BEM) is the mass of the aircraft with the basic equipment, unconsumable fluids and unusable fuel and oil.",
    "id": "23f86dc2-d25d-4e12-9e48-da9511f69e83"
  },
  {
    "question": "What would you do in the event of an engine failure below V1, and what would your initial actions be?",
    "answer": "Assuming I'm performing single pilot operations:\n\n- power idle,\n\n- max brakes (and reversers if available),\n\n-maintain directional control using rudder input,\n\n- After coming to a full stop set parking break.\n\n- Inform ATC 'Stopping'.\n\n- Initiate the appropriate process to diagnose the problem (ECAM, NITS DODAR, checklists....).\n\n- When performing multi pilot operations the actions performed by me will depend with my current role: PF, PM and/or CM1 CM2.",
    "id": "ffb6ec3f-6c4b-474b-8bed-e09d0f9d5a2e"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you calculate the Operating Mass?",
    "answer": "OM = DOM + crew and fuel",
    "id": "642082c1-1df9-469e-b313-365393681ed8"
  },
  {
    "question": "What’s the temperature at FL150 according to ISA?",
    "answer": "-15°C \n\nbecause:\n\n-2°C per 1000 feet gives -30°C.\n\nISA: 15°C at sea level - 30°C = -15°C at FL150",
    "id": "a82b057f-a330-404f-a50d-d63764f6835f"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does a swept wing stall first?",
    "answer": "At the tip",
    "id": "42d028db-fb12-4736-bc50-81cf86908d53"
  },
  {
    "question": "What setting would you set the trim to for long range cruise?",
    "answer": "Nose up",
    "id": "230b68f9-0ee4-49c5-b713-6b167dcaa64d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is adverse yaw?",
    "answer": "When rolling the aircraft the up-going wing will experience more drag than the down-going wing. This will result in a yawing moment that directly opposes the desired direction of turn. (i.e.: rolling left will cause a right yaw.)",
    "id": "b4607e03-5268-49c5-8cfc-f6905a69c2f8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some wings, flaps and rudders are indented, why?",
    "answer": "To increase the strength of the surfaces.\n\nThe same strategy is employed by plastic water bottles, by adding ridges to a surface you increase it's structural rigidity",
    "id": "0926468e-b9c8-43ed-bb99-38eb1a9a2333"
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain what coffin corner is and what happens when reaching the coffin corner?",
    "answer": "Occurs at absolute ceiling where low speed buffet and high speed (Mach) buffet are coincident.\n\nWhen reaching the coffin corner, both increasing and decreasing the corner speed will result in a loss of control (either the aircraft stalls, or mach buffeting starts).",
    "id": "4de7f20c-3066-4b4c-8d4f-9912f0000640"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is ACA/H? What ACA/H did you use? Why do we have an ACA/H?",
    "answer": "Asymmetric Committal Altitude/Height is the minimum height needed to establish a positive climb whilst maintaining adequate speed for control and removal of drag during an approach to a landing.\n\nIn the Seneca at Oxford we used 200ft AGL. At this altitude when continuing for landing you selected the landing flaps (check clear runway, on speed, on altitude, landing clearance received).\n\nYou now are committed to land, single engine G/A with flaps 40 and gear down is not possible in a Seneca.",
    "id": "3dfd8a42-0471-48e7-9f0b-54d6b4625aad"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tell me about the last aircraft you flew in.",
    "answer": "Example answer for a candidate with previous Seneca experience:\n\nWeights:\n\nMax all up weight – take off 4570lbs\nMax all up weight – landing 4340lbs\nEmpty weight - 2830lbs\nUsefull load - 1740lbs\n\nSpeeds:\n\nClean stall 66kts with flaps 60kts\nVyse 89kts\nCruise 140kts gear raising 107kts – lowering 129kts.\nVne 195\n\nThe 6 cyclinder teledyne continental turbo- charged, fuel injected engines provide 200 hp at 2575.\n\nLeft engine rotated clockwise and right anti clockwise.\n\nNo critical engine, RayGay turbo’s 42” MAP, 40” limit at lower levels, cowl flaps provide cooling and has 3 positions, open mid and closed.\n\nAvgas 100/130\n\nProps 2 or 3 blade, constant speed, hydraulically actuated, fully feathering.\n\nOil keeps props at fine pitch, gas and air keep the rpm towards feather. Takes 6 seconds to feather and must happen before locks engage at 800 rpm.\n\nLimit load factor 3.8G\n\nFuel 2 x 54 (64US) gallons tanks 8 quarts oil max 6 Min\n\nRetractable gear – hydraulic pumps – electrically driven. 6-7 seconds transit\n\nNose gear has 27 degrees castor.\n\nMain wheels 55psi, nose wheel 31psi\n\nCable operated controls, all moving stabilator with anti servo tab which acts as a trim.\n\nFrise ailerons and differential ailerons, up more than down.\n\nManual flaps, 3 settings, 10, 25, 40 degrees.\n\n4.5” – 5.2” hg suction – AH, DI.\n\nHeated lift deflectors and stall warners, anti ice.",
    "id": "614a6fb0-434c-46d2-acec-86c1f2d6424a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are fusible plugs, where are they used, how do they work, why do we have them?",
    "answer": "Fusible plugs offer protection from tire blowouts caused by thermal expansion that is generated in the tire under extra hard braking conditions.",
    "id": "f024e0ba-837f-40a0-8fb7-816d9995930b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is departure?",
    "answer": "Departure is an east-west distance along a parallel line of latitude, other than the equator.\n\nDeparture is calculated by: Change of longitude(minutes) x cosine of latitude.",
    "id": "7a42884e-fe7f-4954-a075-3c3330ab72e5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you explain what a coastal breeze is?",
    "answer": "A coastal breeze is a wind from the sea that develops over land near coasts.\n\nIt is formed by increasing temperature differences between the land and water; these create a pressure minimum over the land due to its relative warmth, and forces higher pressure, cooler air from the sea to move inland.\n\nGenerally, air temperature gets cooler relative to nearby locations as one moves closer to a large body of water.",
    "id": "10cae640-b34b-40c7-9ed5-d0968a6642a2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are wing tip vortices?",
    "answer": "Wingtip vortices are tubes of circulating air that are left behind a wing as it generates lift. \n\nThey are caused by the difference in pressure above and below the wing causing the air to 'escape' from the high pressure area below the wing to the low pressure area above the wing, by rolling around the tip of the wing. This creates a vortex that trails behind the wing.",
    "id": "00d7c076-516b-4f17-a858-2666588c46ce"
  },
  {
    "question": "What clearance do MSA values give?",
    "answer": "They provide at least 1000ft clearance over obstacles within 25NM of the homing facility.",
    "id": "e47da6c1-643c-459f-87d9-1c21da527fcc"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is anhedral?",
    "answer": "Downward inclination of a wing from the root to the tip.",
    "id": "39805c8b-7470-4d2f-96dd-4982c2484f26"
  },
  {
    "question": "Are jet streams there all year round?",
    "answer": "Yes.\n\nThere are permanent jet streams in the...",
    "id": "84447eb5-e832-46c1-aeec-d1da64eca160"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is radiation fog?",
    "answer": "Radiation fog forms on cloudless nights with only very light winds and high relative humidity when the cold ground cools the air above it to its dew point causing condensation (fog).\n\nUsually occurs inland in valleys and low lying areas (as these areas tend to have more moisture) and usually occurs in a high pressure system.",
    "id": "213b7e51-ce19-47e1-aff5-cd1948b705f9"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the lift qualities of a swept wing?",
    "answer": "Poor, because the sweep-back design has the effect of reducing the lift capabilities of the wing.",
    "id": "ea30c90c-d68b-41f4-9efd-b0d9184b3db1"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what speed does Mach tuck occur?",
    "answer": "Mcrit",
    "id": "78b6a90a-6f1e-4239-ab1d-1fca68a1bd1d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the range of a VOR at 32000ft?",
    "answer": "Range = 1.23(√H1 + √H2)\n\n= 1.23 * √32000\n\n= 220 nm",
    "id": "a781fffb-7577-4553-88d1-ae07c54cfb7d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can a helicopter rotor blade stall?",
    "answer": "Yes",
    "id": "d0dbc086-327b-440b-9e51-a17a0492cff6"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you have a fire from the engine in the Warrior, what do you do?",
    "answer": "On the Warrior, I would perform the following items:\n\nthrottle closed\nmixture closed\nfuel selector off\nfuel pump off\nmagnetos off\n(mayday + 7700 if time permits) and check if fire is out\nheater defrost off\nbatt alt switches off\ntop door latch unlatch\nseat belts erect secure and make a forced landing",
    "id": "4ee5fdea-339d-47dc-8df6-54b98b086677"
  },
  {
    "question": "What navigational instruments does the Boeing 737-800 have?",
    "answer": "IRS / GPS / VOR / DME",
    "id": "bbfa49bb-2789-4a2b-9d33-e268c8ab24f1"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying in a straight line on an airway when your company calls and requests you to return to base, what will you do first?",
    "answer": "Inform ATC.",
    "id": "1726c0f6-5140-4324-82c0-75e4681a340f"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the N1 compressor produce thrust?",
    "answer": "Yes, with the modern high bypass turbofans the N1 compressor works as a huge propeller, it takes a big mass of air and gives it a relative small acceleration.\n\nAround 70% of the air will bypass the core of the engine, only 30% of air will be compressed further and will eventually go through the combustion chamber.",
    "id": "f663b962-9a9a-4f62-8cd2-28610adf55eb"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does a wet runway have on V1?",
    "answer": "V1 is lower when the runway is wet than when the runway is dry, because of the longer ASDR on a wet runway.",
    "id": "cdd57175-53fa-4cf5-bde6-f3ece4e4b969"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is convergency?",
    "answer": "Meridians converge from their maximum distance apart (at the equator) to the poles where they meet.\n\nGreat circles are the shortest distance between two points and convergency represents the change in direction experienced between those points.",
    "id": "9efa8b9f-95ab-49fb-bfdc-983502371451"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the height of the tropopause according to ISA?",
    "answer": "36,090ft in ISA",
    "id": "dd38d449-cb28-4b33-9f26-b9232ede0228"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you where picking up 10.000 litres of fuel in Newfoundland (cold weather), and 10.000 litres of fuel in Lima, Peru (hot weather), where would you have picked up the most fuel?",
    "answer": "In Newfoundland. With cold weather density increases, therefore you would pick up a higher mass in Newfoundland.",
    "id": "18316e4b-fcef-4c83-9c12-600d482a1777"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does a swept wing increase Mcrit?",
    "answer": "A swept wing makes the velocity vector normal to the leading edge a shorter distance than the chordwise resultant.",
    "id": "ed03ec3c-430b-4342-9a0d-28529aec109f"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which way do jet streams travel?",
    "answer": "From West to East\n\nEast to West (In Africa during the summer)",
    "id": "d1d58e72-ff87-41e8-a820-c2093c3da1c9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does a jet have a critical engine? Why yes or no?",
    "answer": "No, there is no P-factor (asymmetric blade effect) as on a propeller-driven aircraft.",
    "id": "85837131-1d36-4025-853b-5ea975e8a3bc"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a Mach trimmer do?",
    "answer": "A Mach trimmer automatically compensates for Mach tuck above Mcrit.",
    "id": "4dbd65b9-da68-4fd1-8003-94aa26595d18"
  },
  {
    "question": "At high altitudes, what speed do aircrafts climb on?",
    "answer": "Mach number",
    "id": "5a896a45-4de0-4784-9f87-c5a7f0a24303"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe the take off segments.",
    "answer": "1st segment starts at screen height and finishes at gear retracted.\n\n2nd segment starts when the gear is retracted and finishes when acceleration alt is reached (min. 400ft max 1000ft) speed V2.\n\n3rd segment starts at acceleration alt, minimum 400ft, and finishes when the flaps are retracted.\n\n4th segment starts when the flaps are retracted, MCT is set and finishes at the 1500ft.",
    "id": "dae1b539-b669-47a1-b98c-adf24de37e25"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you climb to FL300 at a constant IAS of 250kts, what would happen to the TAS?",
    "answer": "TAS will increase.",
    "id": "489af326-d34f-4938-a82b-cd65b2829da3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do airplanes have to guard against reaching Mcrit?",
    "answer": "Barber pole on the ASI, flying at a Mach number at altitude and audible warnings.",
    "id": "aa397929-b07a-477f-a0d1-aa53c9d4aa15"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between angle of attack and angle of incidence?",
    "answer": "Angle of attack is the angle between the chord of the aerofoil and the relative airflow.\n\nAngle of incidence is the angle between the chord and the aircrafts longitudinal datum.",
    "id": "7029be46-7ffd-4571-b33f-3f965693b05d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Would you be happy if VMCG is higher than V1?",
    "answer": "No, because if your critical engine fails at V1 you have to continue your takeoff roll, but because you’re under VMCG you are unable to maintain directional control.",
    "id": "c27b92e2-6f68-46f7-b60b-37258757a558"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will happen if the primer of your engine/fuel system kept operating?",
    "answer": "A variable pitch propeller provides an optimum angle of attack for the propeller blades for a longer range which reduces fuel usage, fixed pitch propellers only have a certain rpm.",
    "id": "6bcde3fc-4f3d-4d91-bf02-9946664d93a0"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is anhedral used instead on some aircraft?",
    "answer": "Anhedral:\n\ncompensates for the wing sweep\nimproves roll maneuverability",
    "id": "8879ad72-9dbd-4e65-af27-a9bf7705679c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approach category speeds are defined by which formula?",
    "answer": "This speed is defined to be equal to the greater of stall speed (Vso) multiplied by 1.3, or stall speed (Vs1g) multiplied by 1.23.\n\nThe landing configuration that is to be taken into consideration can be defined by either the operator or by the aeroplane manufacturer but is most commonly assigned by the manufacturer.",
    "id": "a800a282-92a0-4d1a-a8e2-f3038fd85902"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the cabin altitude of the Boeing 737 on a cruise flight level?",
    "answer": "8.000ft",
    "id": "6e7976ed-e360-47a4-8ae8-18a677bd8947"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of operating a one aircraft type fleet, why don’t we use an A320 / B737 mixed fleet?",
    "answer": "The FMA indicates what system is controlling the aircraft and what mode is operational.",
    "id": "5d6e0f04-95d6-4ce6-873a-7599a30805db"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are at the locator, on glide-scope, on localiser, but your altimeter is reading 500ft high what could be the cause of this?",
    "answer": "False glide slope.",
    "id": "5bc7a648-6ed3-44ca-9f0b-b66a5436ddaa"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does an IRS work?",
    "answer": "An IRS is an Inertial Reference System  which consists of accelerometers, gyroscopes (laser) and a position computer.\n\nThe computer calculates the aircrafts position by direction and velocity sensed by the accelerometers from the initial latitude and longitude input.\n\nAn IRS enables the aircraft to fly great circle tracks and to navigate accurately across vast expanses where no ground based navigation aids are available.",
    "id": "aca4496b-204e-491c-a5c5-ffc79c19bee6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why will a jet usually not fly at 41.000 feet?",
    "answer": "Because of the distance which has to be covered to reach 41.000 feet which may not be convenient for a short flight.\n\nOn long flights it is more typical to fly at 41.000 feet when the aircraft weight and performance allows.",
    "id": "fcecfe9c-ac10-4950-b9e8-6390ea2d1c1e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wings does the Boeing 737-800 use?",
    "answer": "Swept back wings",
    "id": "18503345-c22e-4608-850c-677fa8cdefe4"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does a jet engine/gas turbine work?",
    "answer": "Forward motion forces air into the intake which is a convergent duct where it is compressed (causing a temperature rise).\n\nFuel is added and combustion takes place increasing the volume. The expanding gasses accelerate to the atmosphere through the exhaust duct nozzle producing a propulsive jet.",
    "id": "172c15b5-2d33-4349-93dc-9d676efa76d2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the typical range of an NDB?",
    "answer": "Average range over land 20 - 25 miles.\n\nRange for an NDB can be calculated with:\n\n2√power output in Watts = Range (Land)\n3√ power output in Watts = Range (Water)",
    "id": "980713a1-5813-49dd-bc8a-5cb84dbeb4a6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an anti-servo tab?",
    "answer": "An anti-servo tab works in the opposite way to a servo tab.\n\nIt deploys in the same direction as the control surface, making the movement of the control surface more difficult and requires more force applied to the controls by the pilot.",
    "id": "3feb167c-9404-4209-9c54-0ed225ffb63e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What increases Mcrit?",
    "answer": "Swept wings, thin wings.",
    "id": "be11e763-18ee-4a69-9b09-7e2ed333e38c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What uses the most battery power, to transmit or to receive?",
    "answer": "Transmitting uses more power.",
    "id": "a2975fac-72be-4fca-adf1-8458ca74f05c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is alternate air? And what is its relation with the air filter?",
    "answer": "Alternate air is....",
    "id": "27fbf7d7-fc09-49f7-a00d-02738fec1f35"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which flight will take the shortest time, from London to New York or New York to London?",
    "answer": "New York to London (flying east) would take less time because of the Polar front westerly jet stream.",
    "id": "e9ccab7e-74fd-4132-9c09-09701be9ee4c"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tailplane of a Seneca has an elevator and a trim tab, what does a Boeing 737 have?",
    "answer": "The Boeing 737 has an all moving horizontal stabilizer.",
    "id": "523f5487-69a6-4dae-960c-860b86c8eebe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Being an excellent pilot, if I can fly at VMCA, do I need a V2 speed?",
    "answer": "Yes, for safety you will need a V2 speed.",
    "id": "4132ef5d-fc83-45c6-b30f-3e90d3c3272f"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a yaw damper?",
    "answer": "Boots on the leading edges inflate (6 seconds) to break the ice dissipating it into the airflow.\n\nPowered by the gyro pressure system.",
    "id": "6d3954ed-5ead-4453-8cb5-38e4812f5f47"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a turbo fan?",
    "answer": "A turbofan is a type of jet engine, similar to a turbojet.\n\nIt essentially consists of a ducted fan with a smaller diameter turbojet engine mounted behind it that powers the fan.\n\nPart of the airstream from the ducted fan passes through the turbojet where it is burnt to power the fan, but the majority of the flow bypasses it, and produces most of the thrust. They are mainly used commercially because they are highly efficient and relatively quiet in operation.",
    "id": "6ce2a281-d844-4046-91e5-bb176182c385"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can VMCG be lower than V1? Explain.",
    "answer": "Yes, VMCG has to be equal to or less than V1 to ensure the aircraft could maintain runway heading having suffered an engine failure at or above V1 when the aircraft is committed to takeoff.",
    "id": "75678d64-8f87-407a-a194-4e931a4dba39"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the range of a VOR?",
    "answer": "VOR stations are fairly short range: the signals are line of sight between transmitter and receiver and are useful for up to 200 miles.\n\nEach station broadcasts a VHF radio composite signal including the navigation signal, station's identifier and voice, if so equipped.",
    "id": "02126b43-3290-4f34-9f27-b94f7483731b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the effects on the human body in case of depressurisation?",
    "answer": "Hypoxia, a lack of oxygen to tissues of the body due to low partial pressure at altitude.\n\nSymptoms are: blue lips, apparent personality change, impaired judgement, muscular impairment, short term memory loss, sensory loss, hyperventilation, unconsciousness.\n\nOther possible effects:\n\n- Baurotrauma\n\n- Lung damage",
    "id": "eee82f32-5e1b-481e-a8e7-46503408b5ca"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is DA?",
    "answer": "Decision altitude (precision), the altitude at which a decision must be made during an ILS, MLS, or PAR instrument approach to either continue the approach or to execute a missed approach.",
    "id": "e61b2245-9d0f-4a40-9aab-fc4c620ea0e6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are TORA, TODA, ASDA clearways, stopways, and screen heights?",
    "answer": "TORA= Takeoff Run Available, the length of runway declared available and suitable for the ground run of an aeroplane taking off.\n\nTODA= Takeoff Distance Available, the length of the take off run available (TORA) plus the length of the clearway, if available.\n\nASDA= Accelerated Stop Distance Available, the length of the takeoff run plus the length of the stopway, if available.\n\nA clearway is an area beyond the paved runway, free of obstructions and under the control of the airport authorities. The length of the clearway may be included in the length of the takeoff distance available (Take Off Distance Available (TODA)). For example, if a paved runway is 2000 m long and there are 400 m of clearway beyond the end of the runway, the takeoff distance available is 2400 m long.\n\nThe stopway is an area beyond the runway which can be used for deceleration in the event of a rejected takeoff.\n\nScreen height: TODR is the distance from the brake release point to the point where the aircraft gains a height of 35 ft above the ground. This 35 ft is what we call the screen height. While 35 ft is the screen height for class A airplanes, it is 50 ft for class B airplanes.\n\nOn a wet runway, the screen height is reduced to 15 ft.",
    "id": "fba61ee9-d29b-4348-ac1c-8ef248aadde3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is thrust produced in a gas turbine engine?",
    "answer": "Mostly in the fan, but also from the exhaust nozzle duct.",
    "id": "79c502af-5929-497c-a52c-2ca3638d6a23"
  },
  {
    "question": "On A high wing anhedral airplane, like a BAE146, and a high wing straight winged aircraft like a Fokker 50, why they don’t have dihedral wings if it has so many advantages?",
    "answer": "A high wing location like the BAE and the Fokker give a natural stable contribution.\n\nThis is because the Center of Gravity is underneath the wing, therefore when disturbed the C.G. provides a positive momentum opposite to the distortion.",
    "id": "21384165-27aa-4366-9321-b35824264321"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure does a pitot tube measure?",
    "answer": "The total pressure (static and dynamic pressure).",
    "id": "ce5e6530-7dcb-43cb-9cb4-a96f414bf6b6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is carb heat an electrical system?",
    "answer": "No. Carburetor heat uses exhaust air to heat air going into the carburetor. No electrics are involved.",
    "id": "f6baf173-1ad2-4b78-a3d4-8f903e2821c1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the advantage of a variable pitch propeller? Why not have a fixed propeller?",
    "answer": "A variable pitch propeller provides an optimum angle of attack for the propeller blades for a longer range which reduces fuel usage. Fixed pitch propellers are easier to produce and maintain, but reach maximum efficient at only one specific airspeed.",
    "id": "4a4974a8-8a05-47f3-8152-100e4c3b56e2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why would someone fly a Rhumb Line track?",
    "answer": "- If no IRS/INS/GPS was available, it’s easier to fly a constant heading (but you will need to apply variation).\n\n- If flying over short distances (as done during your training) the error introduced by flying a rhumb line is insi ",
    "id": "0e92fc55-4e3c-44f3-860f-c0d15066dd53"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the yaw damper fails and the aircraft experiences Dutch roll, how can the pilot stabilize the aircraft?",
    "answer": "Apply opposite aileron to the direction of the roll.",
    "id": "d30f33a3-1528-431c-b0a6-83c08d627876"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do we measure speed as a Mach number?",
    "answer": "Mach number describes the speed of sound, which changes with the density of the medium it is travelling through.\n\nWhen you reach the speed of sound, the compressibility effect creates a supersonic flow along the wing if you exceed a certain mach number.\n\nThis causes airflow separation and flutter.\n\nIt is therefore much safer and much easier to use a Mach number to express a limit at which compressibility effects start to tear the aircraft apart, as it is a constant value at all altitudes.",
    "id": "342eea4b-1008-4329-bcad-d04c20bed5a5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a Mach trimmer?",
    "answer": "A Mach trimmer is a system that artificially corrects for Mach tuck.",
    "id": "ac94be19-805c-46b5-ad66-a7ea6bd169ec"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you convert between lbs and kg?",
    "answer": "1kg = 2.2lbs",
    "id": "c154a3ea-4bf8-4668-9d51-892683bffc7a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can you tell about adiabatic lapse rates?",
    "answer": "When considering a volume of air, adiabatic lapse rate is the temperature change that is caused by the vertical movement of the volume, andThe Lapse Rate is the rate at which temperature changes with height in the atmosphere.\n\nThe Environmental Lapse Rate (ELR) is according to ISA 2°C per 1000 feet increasing altitude.\n\nFor unsaturated air, the lapse rate is 3°C per 1000 feet, this is called the Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate (DALR).\n\nThe Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate (SALR) is the rate at which saturated air cools with height and is, at low levels and latitudes, 1.8°C per 1000 feet.",
    "id": "1db1d922-f504-4905-a2e0-94d3690be7f0"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the different aircraft categories, speeds and on which speed these categories are based.",
    "answer": "Aircraft categories are based on Vat (in knots):\n\nA <91\n\nB 91-120\n\nC 121-140\n\nD 141-165\n\nE 166 - 210",
    "id": "f491f7f3-bb8d-401b-a4ff-34197d810e0e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation PAPI mean?",
    "answer": "Precision Approach Path Indicator",
    "id": "09058184-d66b-4628-b1c6-817156e1a40c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain the definition “critical engine”.",
    "answer": "The critical engine of a multi-engine, fixed-wing propeller-driven aircraft is the one whose failure would result in the most adverse effects on the aircraft's handling and performance.\n\nDue to the asymmetric blade effect (P-factor), the right-hand engine typically develops its resultant thrust vector at a greater lateral distance from the aircraft's C.G. than the left-hand engine.\n\nThe failure of the left-hand engine will result in a larger yaw effect via the operating right-hand engine, rather than vice-versa, and it is termed the Critical Engine. Since the operating right-hand engine produces a stronger yaw moment, the pilot will need to use larger control deflections in order to maintain aircraft control. Thus, the failure of the critical (left-hand) engine is less desirable than failure of the right-hand engine.\n\nThe operating right-hand engine will produce a more severe yaw towards the dead engine, thus making the failure of the left-hand engine critical.",
    "id": "e8b69f90-3095-479f-85b1-7e91211a63f9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain the Fohn wind.",
    "answer": "A Fohn wind is a warm dry wind that blows down the lee side of a mountain.\n\nInitially, the air temperature cools dry-adiabatically (3°C/1000 ft), until its dew point temperature is reached. Condensation occurs as the air is further forced up the mountain range, resulting in the air cooling saturated-adiabatically (generally considered in the mid-latitudes to be 1.8°C/1000 ft). Clouds and precipitation form. When the air mass reaches the top of the mountain range it has lost a significant amount of its water content and so has a much lower dew point temperature.\n\nAs the air then begins to descend down the lee slope of the mountain the compressed air is initially heated saturated-adiabatically, and in effect the direct reverse to the cooling effect on the windward side occurs. As the air continues leeward and downward from the mountain range, the air, now no longer saturated, is heated dry-adiabatically.\n\nThe resultant wind is dry and warm giving clear conditions at airfields on the lee side of the mountain range.\n\nThe Foehn Effect also may be associated with mountain wave activity.",
    "id": "67be7cc0-3727-4dd2-8f3b-afd16b3ba35a"
  },
  {
    "question": "If turboprops are more efficient aircraft, why do they not climb that high?",
    "answer": "Jet engines are designed to achieve their best specific fuel consumption at high rpm, which can only be achieved at high altitudes where the air density is low.\n\nThrust produced will be low enough to equal the required cruising thrust. Also high altitude gives the best operating conditions for the airframe i.e. minimum drag during the cruise.\n\nTurboprops need relatively dense air for the propellers to work efficiently and at high altitude the density would be too low.",
    "id": "f0d42856-698b-4d6f-b1b0-bba3bcf33586"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation MSA mean?",
    "answer": "Minimum Safe Altitude.",
    "id": "c5402226-6441-4b17-bb4a-2a6b13dbc6e1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is windshear?",
    "answer": "Windshear is a change of wind speed and/or direction from place to place, including updraughts and down draughts.\n\nIt is ussualy characterized by a strong change over a short distance. Windshear can effect the flight path and airspeed and can be hazardous.",
    "id": "871edb3d-49d7-4f6f-91a6-ffd6a9c2bc7d"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a tapered wing, where would the stall occur first?",
    "answer": "At the tip as downwash and spanwise flow effect the angle of attack at each section, but because of the tapered wing the effective angle of attack near the tips is greater than that near the center.",
    "id": "a0abaf34-bbb5-4c2a-be20-5ade7c164910"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why don’t you want to fly your Seneca into a thunderstorm?",
    "answer": "Due to the structural damage that may occur in thunderstorms, due to hail, severe turbulence and severe windshear.\n\nBesides that, lightning strikes may cause damage to electrical systems and severe icing may occur.",
    "id": "45a23a12-1fa9-460a-a131-7644235a7823"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the environmental lapse rate according to ISA?",
    "answer": "1.98°C per 1000ft",
    "id": "ca647783-8e82-4240-833c-f675f1199746"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an FMA used for?",
    "answer": "Bright yellow lights will light up in the cockpit.",
    "id": "e40524b6-4753-4de1-9d4b-5dcbc7306f4a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Mcrit?",
    "answer": "Mcrit is the aircraft’s Mach speed at which the airflow over a wing becomes sonic.",
    "id": "4cc71160-75f0-4d7b-a435-6fa1d7e18f17"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does an aerofoil work?",
    "answer": "An aerofoil is a body shaped to produce an aerodynamic reaction (lift) perpendicular to its direction of motion, for a small resistance (drag) force in that plane. It achieves this by accelerating the flow passing over it, and decelerating the flow passing under it. This change in velocity causes a change in pressure, which in turn generates lift.",
    "id": "ff0e7180-8c7d-4099-8408-c2004563a50f"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a high bypass ratio engine?",
    "answer": "In a high bypass design, the vast majority of the thrust is derived from the ducted fan, rather than from combustion gases expanding in a nozzle.\n\nA high bypass ratio provides a lower thrust specific fuel consumption (grams/sec fuel per unit of thrust in kN using SI units), especially at zero velocity (at takeoff) and at the cruise speed of most commercial jet aircraft.",
    "id": "4125c15b-ee67-4ea2-a938-0ae24307139e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do we use Jeppesen charts/plates?",
    "answer": "Jeppesen charts and plates are simplified and uniform.",
    "id": "ca3cbfd6-48ed-4071-8744-2d4eaf09cd91"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather is associated with windshear?",
    "answer": "CAT\n\nFrontal passage\n\nMicroburst",
    "id": "5e91a1f9-9db4-47c6-9cb5-3e5f1d267f9a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between a supercharger and a turbocharger?",
    "answer": "A turbo charger is externally driven by exhaust back pressure turning a turbine which in turn drives a compressor in the induction manifold to increase the air pressure (constant volume, higher pressure) and is controlled by waste gate.\n\nA supercharger is internally driven by the propellor shaft to compress mixture and is controlled by RPM.",
    "id": "cf0cb9e8-b778-48f1-aa0d-7385ac78a16e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do aircraft have leading edge devices?",
    "answer": "There are 2 types of leading edge devices:\n\n-Slats. Slats are movable surfaces on the leading edge of the wing which when deployed, allow the wing to operate at a higher angle of attack, by delaying separation in the wing upper surface.\n\n-Leading edge flaps (Krueger). Leading edge flaps are hinged on the leading edge of the wing and extend forward and down when deployed. they provide similar benefits as trailing edge flaps, by increasing wing surface area and camber.",
    "id": "45420f3b-ee6c-41e0-ba37-1d72bf32b4e2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do high lift devices do?",
    "answer": "High lift devices increase the lift produced by a wing, allowing the aircraft to operate at lower speed ranges usually for take off and landing.",
    "id": "0804ffdc-a56a-431a-9b08-bce2769ba75e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do the abbreviations TSRA and MIFG mean?",
    "answer": "\n\nTSRA: Thunderstorm with rain\n\n- MIFG: Shallow fog",
    "id": "5ed9a3be-cb57-4f8a-833f-a3b03fc02432"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an NDB?",
    "answer": "Non Directional Beacon, a medium range radio navigation aid that sends out a signal in all directions for an aircraft to home to.",
    "id": "8447d2ff-edf0-4bac-a833-209d05585c0a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does the speed tape on the PFD reads 45kt when the aircraft is stationary?",
    "answer": "The speed is too low for an indication.",
    "id": "df0e219c-6ca9-4caf-8adf-c6002aebf1d8"
  },
  {
    "question": "How accurate are NDB's?",
    "answer": "NDB’s are stations emitting a signal. There is nothing for them to be accurate about. ADF's on the other hand, when tuned to an NDB need to be accurate within +/- 5 degrees.",
    "id": "e8837c30-32ba-4b95-87f9-a96f5dbd461e"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does a stall strip work?",
    "answer": "A stall strip, usually located close to the wing root, causes the airflow to separate at a lower angle of attack and ensures that the wing root stalls before the wing tips.",
    "id": "b63bae18-ae83-45a4-8977-5fffe228f05b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do single engined planes have a VMCG?",
    "answer": "No, VMCG is defined as the minimum control speed on the ground, with one engine inoperative (critical engine on two engine airplanes), takeoff power on other engine(s), using aerodynamic controls only for directional control and thus only applicable to ME aircraft.",
    "id": "63aed1cd-5d85-4344-a869-f85c4f85f4d0"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a Rhumb Line?",
    "answer": "A line across the surface of the earth that cuts all meridians at the same angle. i.e. a track of constant direction.\n\nA straight line on a Mercator chart.",
    "id": "6a2db43d-586a-4f56-9f83-8ab95418bea5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Vs?",
    "answer": "Stall speed is defined as the minimum steady flight speed at which the airplane is controllable.",
    "id": "d189f3e6-a320-4e0b-8f5a-352828224e4b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do you need contingency fuel?",
    "answer": "Contingency fuel is carried to account for additional enroute fuel consumption caused by wind, routing changes or ATM: ATM/CNS restrictions.",
    "id": "47cd1ae3-1102-4ecb-8eaa-4114bb3b726e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What frequency range and band is an NDB in?",
    "answer": "Frequency range from 200-1750kHz, medium and low range frequency bands.",
    "id": "e122a7fd-c26a-44f0-81e6-e9de06a383d3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do the fuel gauges read in kg, but fuel is delivered in litres?",
    "answer": "Because the specific gravity can change with temperature.",
    "id": "62ebad6b-8d62-4e71-9af4-6f3e77ec3ef3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you convert litres to kg?",
    "answer": "Volume of litres x Specific gravity = weight in kg",
    "id": "1985abf4-0df3-49b4-9a8c-f7d08ee1628b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What errors does an NDB suffer from?",
    "answer": "NDB errors:\n\nInterference from other NDB’s\n\n- Static, especially near thunderstorms\n\n- Night effect\nCoastal refraction\n\n- Mountain effect\n\n- Aircraft quadrantal error",
    "id": "2f65fa9d-ac11-4869-bd7d-960af74c8436"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do we calculate mass and balance?",
    "answer": "To be within aircraft design limitations with regards to:\n\nStructural limitations\n\nStability\n\nTake-off and landing performance",
    "id": "c00e7c54-3b90-48ec-a469-b8b06e300f95"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a Great Circle?",
    "answer": "A line of shortest distance between two points on a sphere.",
    "id": "83edb354-52b4-4967-95b9-f55814260230"
  },
  {
    "question": "What sort of weather would you find at an occluded front?",
    "answer": "Low pressure weather, unstable weather.",
    "id": "6838a55c-7cfc-43e3-9cba-5e2c9880b659"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the movement of the center of pressure during/approaching a stall?",
    "answer": "Center of pressure moves forward when approaching a stall.",
    "id": "992c0fb5-c4dd-4b71-ac1a-a3ff8d80c802"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the advantages of an all moving/variable incidence tailplane?",
    "answer": "This provides pitch manoeuvrability.\n\nLongitudinal balancing by the trim system.",
    "id": "0c5a0a3a-53c5-47f7-893e-420d0356a05e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an MCP and what is an FMA?",
    "answer": "The mode control panel is used to select the autothrottle, autopilot, and flight director operating modes. The flight mode annunciator displays current flight modes.",
    "id": "cad39ac2-9040-4753-8643-9b0a224224a7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is the tropopause uniform in height? If not, what height is it at the pole and the equator?",
    "answer": "No, tropopause at the pole is lower (30.000ft) than at the equator (56.000ft)",
    "id": "a2b5367f-7545-4dee-a0ef-b9163db9cf1f"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Vmu?",
    "answer": "Vmu is the minimum unstick speed.\n\nIt is the calibrated airspeed at and above which the airplane can safely lift off the ground and continue the takeoff. Lift-off is not possible prior to reaching this speed.\n\nVmu is not an operational speed and is established in flight testing only.",
    "id": "a835a680-cc93-4b24-888c-f47633ec2ca4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is VMBE?",
    "answer": "The maximum brake energy speed.\n\nIt is a function of the gross weight, altitude, temperature, runway slope, wind component, and braking configuration.\n\nV1 must be less than VMBE.",
    "id": "fc23b0e0-6d6c-49d8-b834-d139283512c9"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does anti-skid work?",
    "answer": "Antiskid has a detection system that senses the moment a wheel stops rotating.\n\nOnce it senses that the wheel is not rotating, the antiskid system releases brake pressure. This allows the wheel to regain traction with the surface, so that break application can be resumed and prevents complete loss of controllability.",
    "id": "c7539479-082d-4d3b-985f-090e4722f642"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you explain to me what Mach tuck is?",
    "answer": "Mach tuck is a nose-down pitching moment experienced as an aircraft passes Mcrit.\n\nMach tuck is a form of longitudinal instability that is caused by the centre of pressures rearward movement (caused by the shock wave) behind the centre of gravity.",
    "id": "dfdbe339-d4fb-496a-8c3b-96be57f238a1"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you only have a compass, which is easier to navigate along: a line of longitude or a line of latitude?",
    "answer": "A line of latitude.",
    "id": "f9e67246-2c58-4a04-ab84-7cfea87d73f2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the dangers of flying into thunderstorms?",
    "answer": "Dangers of flying into thunderstorms:\n\nSevere wind shear and turbulence (with a risk of structural problems, loss of altitude, loss of airspeed)\nSevere icing\nHail\nLightning strikes (with a risk of damage to electrical systems)\nRadio Communications and Navigation interference from static electricity in thunderstorms",
    "id": "3d20f3f5-658d-4ace-b4b4-a956e39cf705"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does a wing stall?",
    "answer": "A wing stalls because the airflow over the wing’s upper surface separates when the critical angle of attack is reached or exceeded. This causes a reduction in the lift generated by the aerofoil",
    "id": "f1437c25-49cd-4f64-91ec-5a63953b29ee"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is profile drag?",
    "answer": "Profile drag, also known as pressure drag or form drag, is the drag caused by the separation of the boundary layer from a surface and the wake created by that separation.\n\nIt is primarily dependent upon the shape of the object and increases directly with speed as the faster an aircraft moves the more air molecules collide with it.",
    "id": "5684e64f-29aa-4a13-b02a-b9aab4d0b8f1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is DOM?",
    "answer": "The Dry Operating Mass (DOM) is the Basic Empty Mass and the Variable Load, also called the Aircraft Prepared for Service (APS) weight.",
    "id": "19efbc20-a889-4102-8c1c-4a7e223abcff"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the maximum operating ceiling of a typical jet?",
    "answer": "41.000ft",
    "id": "f7ba6a1a-e4ae-44a5-a0ae-ea0a90e213eb"
  },
  {
    "question": "Explain V1, V2, VR, VMCA and VMCG",
    "answer": "V1 is the decision speed (sometimes referred to as critical engine speed or critical engine failure speed) by which any decision to reject a takeoff must be made.\n\nV2 is the takeoff safety speed which must be attained at the 35 ft height at the end of the required runway distance. This is essentially the best one-engine inoperative angle of climb speed for the airplane and is a minimum speed for flight in that condition until at least 400 ft above the ground. V2 shall be at least 1.1 times VMCA, and no less than 1.2 times VS.\n\nVr is defined as the speed at which the rotation of the aircraft should be initiated to takeoff attitude.\n\nVMCA is the minimum control speed in the air and is defined as the minimum speed, whilst in the air, that directional control can be maintained with one engine inoperative (critical engine on two engine aerolanes), operating engine(s) at takeoff power and a maximum of 5 degrees of bank towards the good engine(s).\n\nVMCG is the minimum control speed on the ground and is defined as the minimum speed, whilst on the ground, that directional control can be maintained, using only aerodynamic controls, with one engine inoperative (critical engine on two engine airplanes) and takeoff power applied on the other engine(s).",
    "id": "c418d2ff-beab-4451-be21-1a270612ae7a"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are at the end of the runway with the static ports blocked. What will be the reading on the altimeter after departure?",
    "answer": "The elevation at which the airplane departed from the runway.",
    "id": "9c8bb08b-5c77-429f-a701-76f0aa1cd986"
  },
  {
    "question": "Do airplanes have an optimum C.G.? If yes, where is it?",
    "answer": "Yes, the closer the C.G. is to the rear limit, the less tail down force is required, which means less drag which results in less fuel burn.",
    "id": "65162739-cb7d-4644-8adb-e4b1eed37b91"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is RVSM?",
    "answer": "Reduced Vertical Separation Minima (RVSM) is the reduction, from 2,000 feet to 1,000 feet, of the standard vertical separation required between aircraft flying between flight level 290 (29,000 ft) and flight level 410 (41,000 ft).",
    "id": "226bec7e-0d40-42ae-8aa0-5f07cda1e0ef"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the all moving stabilator work on the Boeing 737 compared a fixed horizontal stabilizer of, for example, the Seneca?",
    "answer": "A moving stabilator allows for wider operating range of the control surface, which is of great importance in aircraft with a large range of operating speeds.\n\nCompared to a fixed horizontal stabilizer, when trimmed, the moving stabilitor will produce less drag, reducing fuel consumption.",
    "id": "4e476e2f-513f-480f-aab1-5f72bdc9b97a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the critical angle of attack?",
    "answer": "The critical angle of attack is the angle of attack which produces maximum lift coefficient.\n\nThis is also called the \"stall angle of attack\".",
    "id": "f5fa0e72-3868-4a06-b3fe-72e47c6584bd"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can you go through DA or MDA?",
    "answer": "You can go through a DA, but not a MDA.\n\nA Decision Height, used in precision approaches, defines the point where a go around should be performed. It accounts for the altitude loss during the initial seconds of the go around maneuver.\n\nThe MDA does not account for this and assumes the pilot will never go below this altitude. When performing a CDFA most operators establish a Derived Decision altitude (DDA) to account for the extra lost altitude.",
    "id": "ab6db6d9-b877-4b81-8f7e-5d695ca4eb33"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are NDB powered so that they only have a range between 15-25 miles?",
    "answer": "NDB’s can suffer from a lot of errors.",
    "id": "06337533-fabe-4a43-9823-704d1dced8e0"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is wing loading?",
    "answer": "Wing loading is the loaded weight of the aircraft divided by the area of the wing.\n\nThe faster an aircraft flies, the more lift is produced by each unit area of the wing. Correspondingly, the landing and take-off speeds will be higher and the high wing loading also decreases maneuverability.",
    "id": "ed95e672-f6ff-4c9c-9a8d-646e63a3971d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do jet aircraft fly as high and fast as possible?",
    "answer": "Because the air is less dense thus the TAS is higher for a given power setting and for this reason modern jet aircraft are designed to be most efficient at high altitude.",
    "id": "669d4ba9-1d5a-4ac1-9b3a-be6d42bf4738"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you prefer, a high or low wingload?",
    "answer": "The assessor was trying to get to the approach where you need flaps and slats to increase S (lower wingload) in order to be able to fly a lower speed.",
    "id": "fe16cf1b-82d3-4821-889c-90afbae4d920"
  },
  {
    "question": "When would you expect windshear?",
    "answer": "Cumulonimbus clouds\n\nThunderstorms\n\nVirga",
    "id": "fb93c051-27f9-4040-b213-bdecb683070c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an isobar?",
    "answer": "A line on a meteorologic chart that joins places of equal sea level pressure (QNH).",
    "id": "115df748-0c22-4e96-8bf0-83089437e1f8"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is EGPWS?",
    "answer": "Enhanced Ground Proximity Warning System, provides a greater level of detection than GPWS.\n\nEGPWS is capable of ‘looking ahead’ to identify potential risks on the aircraft flight path as it includes a terrain and obstacle database.",
    "id": "afd68d07-5b90-4611-a713-62d149fd7375"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of Pilot Monitoring?",
    "answer": "To monitor the flight management and aircraft control actions of the Pilot Flying and carry out support duties such as communications and check-list reading.",
    "id": "6f7fef67-b6e6-434f-9928-f7d278cf9fd7"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are winglets and what is the advantage of winglets?",
    "answer": "They are aerodynamically efficient surfaces located at the wing tips, designed to reduce induced drag and increase fuel efficiency.\n\nThey increase efficiency by reducing the size of the wingtip vortices, which are created by the difference between the pressure on the upper surface of the wing and that on the lower surface.",
    "id": "3b1ba81a-df7a-4e9a-a04d-c15a09820eb0"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is MDA?",
    "answer": "Minimum decent altitude (non-precision), the lowest altitude, expressed in feet above mean sea level to which descent is authorised on final approach or during circle-to-land maneuvering in execution of a standard instrument approach procedure where no electronic glideslope is provided.\n\nIf not visual between MDA and MAPt, a Go-around must be initiated.",
    "id": "bb3c5acc-e148-4c39-82fa-d685d9fccb57"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average temperature at 25,000ft according to ISA?",
    "answer": "-35°C",
    "id": "5127f857-8623-4446-aaea-87d1405bf3f5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is the Seneca turbocharged?",
    "id": "e29e3945-8568-4351-9be2-45241b204d83"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying your light twin, how would you ensure minimum obstacle clearance if your engine fails on take off? How would you do this, or, where can you find the relevant information?",
    "answer": "In the airplane documents, as the airplane is certificated regarding performance to be able to fly blue line speed (or Vyse) in this situation, so I would climb at this speed to ensure minimum obstacle clearance.",
    "id": "67ff9585-00cc-4e0b-8ae0-6cf6c1ab3980"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are on a flight from Stansted to Amsterdam and just after T/O you are at your cleared level of 2000ft when you have a complete radio failure. What are your actions?",
    "answer": "First continue on the SID and try all available resources to check if you have a complete radio failure.\n\nIf so, squawk 7600 and return towards the airport.",
    "id": "2ce365e3-f867-4338-9e8a-a58b9cd89d10"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are SOP's? And why do you think Airlines have SOP's?",
    "answer": "SOP's are Standard Operating Procedures, they provide safety, uniformity and work ethics.",
    "id": "f912cb12-6a36-49fe-82a0-231f422652d5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you need to descend from MDA on a non-precision approach?",
    "answer": "You will need to have a clearance, to be stable and visual.",
    "id": "a3cc24cc-0849-4ee8-ae48-d948e944d67a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Is the landing gear in the Seneca electrically or hydraulically operated?",
    "id": "6f3bb7b5-a1c8-4901-a6e3-5032ca967e83"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a METAR?",
    "answer": "A METAR is an observation of the actual weather given by a meteorological observer at that aerodrome.",
    "id": "20dc8ef8-e9dc-41b1-a570-2d4e60d5d32f"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the hydraulic systems of the Boeing 737 called?",
    "answer": "Hydraulic system A and hydraulic system B.",
    "id": "5dd40a23-13fb-433e-a4fd-7033c5c65381"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are the indications on an FMA preferred over an MCP?",
    "answer": "Always make sure to update yourself with the latest information on these type of questions.\n\nCFM56-7 series with a max takeoff thrust of 27,300lb.\n\nThese engines have higher thrust, improved efficiency, and lower maintenance costs than its predecessor, the CFM56-3 series.\n\n180 minutes extended range (ETOPS).\n\nBypass ratio 5.5:1",
    "id": "e231f9e9-af38-49f1-a126-c5218032af0b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do some airplanes have dihedral wings?",
    "answer": "Dihedral provides:\n\nLateral stability (during a roll)\nWing clearance, wingtip to ground has more space",
    "id": "3244ac6b-20db-4ca6-b31d-7279bd56887d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is CRM?",
    "answer": "Crew Resource Management (CRM) is the effective use of all available resources for flight crew personnel to assure a safe and efficient operation, reducing error, avoiding stress and increasing efficiency.",
    "id": "0ea4436d-7a66-467d-9c71-cdbd1bf79e72"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the Boeing 737 have a critical engine?",
    "answer": "No, there is no P-factor (asymmetric blade effect) as on a propeller-driven aircraft.",
    "id": "da86e13a-9400-4281-b33f-d848f9ad052e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a VOR? What frequency range and band is it in?",
    "answer": "VHF Omnidirectional Radio Range (VOR) is defined as VHF Omnidirectional Radio Range, an aircraft navigation system operating in the VHF band.\n\nVOR's are assigned radio channels between 108.0 MHz and 117.95 MHz (with 50 kHz spacing); this is in the very high frequency (VHF) range.",
    "id": "8919ea93-bbd3-4c1c-bbf5-2d2335a18306"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the components that make up a fuel plan for a minimum-fuel trip?",
    "answer": "Taxi, trip, contingency, reserve and extra fuel.",
    "id": "0e7108a1-daa2-46e4-b4f9-f5efc6a184b9"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does an airspeed indicator work and which errors can an airspeed indicator experience?",
    "answer": "The airspeed indicator uses part of the aircraft's pitot-static system to measure and compare the dynamic air pressure between air moving into the pitot tube and static air pressure measured in the case. \n\nThe ASI is calibrated to ISA at MSL and represents the dynamic pressure as indicated airspeed in knots per hour.\n\nASI errors can originate and vary from:\n\nInstrument\nPressure\nDensity\nCompressibility\nManeuver\nBlocked pitot static system",
    "id": "d3a7de1e-21f5-41ee-8943-63f7dc171f34"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL350 and the temperature reads -30°C, is the aircraft at its optimum temperature?",
    "answer": "No because it is warmer, according to ISA temperature should be -55°C",
    "id": "a3f05122-2655-4753-a34a-7d0eec4df26b"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you explain to your neighbour what the difference is between a precision and a non-precision approach?",
    "answer": "A precision approach uses both lateral (from left to right) and vertical guidance. A non-precision approach only uses lateral guidance.",
    "id": "3a73ed5b-3255-4b01-be62-72c77203776d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What performance category was your last aircraft? How are airplanes classified?",
    "answer": "Note: this question was asked to a candidate with previous Seneca experience, make sure to be able to answer this question for your previous aircraft type.\n\nSeneca is class A.\n\nAircraft are classified according to their Vat.",
    "id": "f40b4285-5559-426d-8f5b-37dbc8b116e9"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does speed change from IAS to Mach?",
    "answer": "At FL260",
    "id": "8b5fe303-15c3-4a04-96b1-a88e34e4fe17"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the problems associated with icing?",
    "answer": "Drag penalties (additional weight)\n\nLess controllability",
    "id": "0204ab96-226a-46ff-838d-c6c90f68f75f"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have lost both alternators, how long would the battery last and what would you do?",
    "answer": "30 minutes, I would land as soon as possible.",
    "id": "f18bb064-b6bc-4d76-8865-e162a9b31e68"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relevance of the mass and balance document?",
    "answer": "It’s an official document for the safety of the flight.\n\nA copy of this document needs to remain on the ground.",
    "id": "e7e10eac-a294-48b1-8621-3f711d1d3d72"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you navigate if all VOR's and NDB's en route fail?",
    "answer": "With the IRS/INS/GPS or visually.",
    "id": "aab1522f-18f0-46c9-bb12-915ffd837e21"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the critical point?",
    "answer": "The critical point (CP) is a point on a track where it is as quick to go on as it is to turn back.\n\nAlso known as ETP (Equal Time Point) and PET (Point of Equal Time).",
    "id": "b42481f3-6aee-4ced-a6f4-3d58f44fab05"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tell me, I was looking out the window and I saw white strokes coming out of the engines at cruising level, but I didn’t see it from an aircraft taking off, why is that and what is the difference?",
    "answer": "Those are contrails.\n\nThe jet engine exhaust gases consist of carbon dioxide and water vapour.\n\nAt high altitudes the wator vapour gets released in a very cold environment. This can cause the air to be saturated with water vapour and then condenses. If cold enough the condense can freeze into white droplets. This forms the contrails.",
    "id": "6a43d5eb-8963-4afa-93a7-0594b38d267a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can you tell about occluded fronts?",
    "answer": "Occluded fronts are formed during the process of cyclogenesis when a cold front overtakes a warm front. When this occurs, the warm air is separated (occluded) from the cyclone center at the Earth's surface.\n\nOccluded fronts usually form around mature low pressure areas.",
    "id": "1c7165db-4c09-49d9-83b8-9b783b4633b3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does windshear show on the weather radar?",
    "answer": "No",
    "id": "b4bc9375-8eb1-4f20-993d-3418820bc994"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a jet stream?",
    "answer": "Jet streams are narrow bands of high-speed upper thermal winds at very high altitudes.",
    "id": "9c9f95c6-1415-453b-aea3-b6eeb4c19782"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are airplanes wary of windshear?",
    "answer": "Airplanes can get uncontrollable during windshear.",
    "id": "9b4a9d24-27ca-42c3-9dd8-2b4b1b2854c5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tell us what ranges the glideslope and localiser beams are checked out to?",
    "answer": "Glideslope: 329.15-335Mhz UHF 8 degrees either side, 10NM\n\nLocaliser: 108.10-111.95Mhz VHF 35 degrees either side, 17NM",
    "id": "0405c6a7-c744-4aa9-bd63-07a993ede2b7"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a moment arm?",
    "answer": "The distance from the datum to the point at which the weight of a component acts.",
    "id": "bef32c11-31b3-47f2-aab9-f1ed2c885079"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you take off on a two engine airplane with no engine failure and are below VMCA, will you have directional control?",
    "answer": "Yes, some directional control as we still have two functioning engines.",
    "id": "19017dad-2a92-46e5-a1ef-2e50d8062d0b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is density altitude? and what is pressure altitude?",
    "answer": "Density altitude is pressure altitude corrected for temperature.\n\nPressure altitude is the indicated altitude when an altimeter is set to 29.92 (1,013.2 mb).",
    "id": "e5dd6aca-107a-46e2-8144-7b7c8056d047"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are contrails formed?",
    "answer": "Their formation is most often triggered by freezing water vapour from the exhaust of aircraft engines.",
    "id": "e9f0bc38-3c1b-4111-8121-194b120bd1de"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the fuel capacity of the Boeing 737–800?",
    "answer": "20.020 litres (twenty thousand and twenty litres), about 15 tons.",
    "id": "e65270ac-09c5-4807-84b7-2ddfff85a271"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the disadvantages of a swept wing?",
    "answer": "Swept wings have:\n\n- Poor lift qualities\n- Higher stall speeds\n\n- Speed instability at low speeds\n\n- A wing-tip stalling tendency",
    "id": "88986238-a560-40f1-bbae-ea5c5426d670"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the G-limits of the Boeing 737-800?",
    "answer": "+2.5G / -1.0G",
    "id": "9a44014c-aff4-4b30-b762-c13207980f62"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the optimum ISA cruise altitude for the Boeing 737?",
    "answer": "To varify the nose gear position (up or down).",
    "id": "062deb2b-70ff-47c9-bde9-8c52f447e304"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does an ILS work?",
    "answer": "An ILS (Instrument Landing System) is defined as a precision runway approach aid based on two radio beams which together provide pilots with both vertical and horizontal guidance during an approach to land.\n\nThe ILS aerials transmit two lobes. For a pilot on final, the lobe to his right is modulated at a frequency of 150 Hz and the one to his left at 90 Hz. The point where the lobes meet is the centre line of the runway. As the signals on the lobe move from the centre line to either side, their amplitude increases. This means the magnitude of their depth modulation increases. The depth modulation can be considered as a percentage. For example, if an aircraft receives a 15% depth modulated signal from the left and a 5% depth modulated signal from the right, the difference of modulation becomes 10% to the left. This electrical imbalance is sent to the aircraft and the localizer needle is designed in such a way that it will show a deflection to the opposite direction, telling the pilot to go to the right.\n\nWhen on the centre line, the modulation difference is zero and the needle centres itself.\n\nThe glide slope or the glide path provides the pilot with vertical guidance. The glide slope is set such that a glide slope angle of 3 degrees is maintained by the pilot. The needle of the slope moves up, if the aircraft is too low and moves down if it is too much above the required path. The glide slope is on the UHF band (329.15 - 335 Mhz).\n\nThe glide slope operates the same way as the localizer. The only difference is that the lobes are emitted on the vertical plane. The upper lobe is modulated at 90 Hz while the bottom one at 150 Hz. Exactly the same way as before, the needle of the slope moves based on the difference in depth modulation. As like before when the modulation difference is nil, the glide needle moves to the very centre of the instrument.",
    "id": "cc1199cb-b442-49f1-843c-5e80619e6320"
  },
  {
    "answer": "Because usually the heated air bypasses the air filter, therefore it is possible for dust to enter the engine and so exposing the engine to unnecessary engine wear.",
    "id": "875cf9fc-dc90-446f-8da8-19572d3e0aae"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does TCAS work?",
    "answer": "TCAS works by sending interrogations to other aircraft's transponders.\n\nThe transponder will reply to the interrogation in a similar way it responds to radar. From the time difference between the interrogation and the reply, the distance to the other aircraft is calculated. The reply itself contains the altitude of the other aircraft.\n\nThe distance and the altitude difference with the other aircraft is tracked to identify a trend which may result in a TA or eventually a RA.",
    "id": "23e3862d-70b8-46ab-8d5a-332acccbc1a7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is there an over boost protection on the Piper PA34 Seneca?",
    "answer": "To protect the engine from blowing up as it is easy to open the throttles to far during take off at sea level.",
    "id": "618f6e64-ab52-418a-8f4d-79bb16210ad8"
  },
  {
    "question": "With 10 minutes to go to the destination, you're being advised by ATC that you will have to hold.",
    "answer": "Fuel, speed and holding entry.",
    "id": "e7d27a6f-cbc0-45c0-b9c6-d9c3a1be4713"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Point of No Return (PNR)?",
    "answer": "The point during a flight at which an aircraft is no longer capable of returning to the airfield from which it took off due to fuel considerations.\n\nBeyond this point the aircraft must proceed to some other destination.",
    "id": "ce351dc7-f66a-4db7-b087-d26fb59b9c5e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Could a Seneca fly to the South of France without stopping for extra fuel?",
    "answer": "No",
    "id": "19cad82d-c6ef-4e61-8994-d3c62d8c352b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the screen height for a single engine?",
    "answer": "35 ft\n\n---\n\nFor Reference:\n\n- 50ft for Class B or A (<15° AoB at take-off or normal landings)\n\n- 35ft for Class A (dry take-off or steep approach)\n\n- 15ft for Class A (wet take-off)",
    "id": "ec51a95f-90d5-4a09-bb85-708e13cc83c5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you know about carb icing? Would you experience it today?",
    "answer": "Carb icing can occur in the engine induction system and in the carburettor of piston engines.\n\nRegarding the second question, mention the conditions in which carb icing can occur and if it would be possible on that particular day.\n\nConditions for carb icing: when OAT is between -10 & +30, with high humidity (greater than 40%) and/or visible moisture.",
    "id": "f6feb495-4589-4d39-acfd-a38b81a70cff"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is advection fog?",
    "answer": "Advection fog occurs when moist air passes over a cool surface by advection (wind) and is cooled.\n\nIt is common as a warm front passes over an area with significant snowpack, but it is most common at sea when tropical air encounters cooler waters, including areas of cold water upwelling, such as along the coast of California.",
    "id": "6b664ff8-e43d-46ba-96a1-4189b28e4b0d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What angle of sweep do our aircraft have?",
    "answer": "25°",
    "id": "d17a6348-9cf3-48a1-a504-f6926423e7ae"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do Jeppesen get the information from to make their charts and plates?",
    "answer": "Government sources.",
    "id": "82817eeb-70d8-42f1-8719-a0082089a104"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you calculate the range of a VOR?",
    "answer": "By using the formula: Range (nm) = 1.23(√H1 + √H2)\n\nH1=height of transmitter (feet)\n\nH2=height of receiver (feet)",
    "id": "1968365f-a822-4373-84e6-5ceb2ea16f53"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an orographic cloud?",
    "answer": "An orographic cloud is formed as the air rises up the slope and will often envelope the summit.\n\nWhen the air is humid, some of the moisture will fall on the windward slope and on the summit of the mountain.",
    "id": "64af0cdc-6391-4fb5-971f-98ed37e255f0"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the forces acting on an aircraft in flight?",
    "answer": "Lift, Drag, Weight and Thrust.",
    "id": "01d4436f-3034-40ef-ae2d-ae38843f9f95"
  },
  {
    "question": "What produces the maximum glide range?",
    "answer": "Flying at Vmd. At this speed the aircraft is flying at the maximum ratio of Lift and Drag, maximizing the potential energy consumption in terms of distance travelled.",
    "id": "33c8397e-06b6-44f0-8914-d6bdde3cb681"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of weight on the glide range?",
    "answer": "The glide range is not affected by the weight. Howver Vmd is. The heavier the aircraft, the higher the Vmd.",
    "id": "01856f8a-da58-427b-8893-0f92284d37c1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is rate of climb/descent?",
    "answer": "It's vertical velocity of the aircraft usually expressed in feet per minute.",
    "id": "1a0b076e-7e50-4d07-aef7-7cfd9c56fdba"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of weight on rate of descent? ",
    "answer": "To be the most efficient, aircraft descend at Vmd. Vmd increases with Weight, and therefore the rate of descent increases as well with weight.",
    "id": "2424a743-d013-42e1-a232-c61ac845c8a3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an aerofoil chord line?",
    "answer": "A straight line conecting the leading edge with the trailing edge of an aerofoil.",
    "id": "3dca3323-134a-4405-875f-85462dbc2e2e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the mean chord line?",
    "answer": "It's the wing area divided by the wing span.",
    "id": "d7b69389-d18a-4baa-a680-840ca3ef66fb"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the mean camberine?",
    "answer": "a line extending from the leading edge to the trailing edge equidistent from the upper and lower surface of the aerofoil.",
    "id": "7df6b78d-5e7c-4156-a6d4-c6e93d39d7a6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the angle of incidence?",
    "answer": "The angle between between the chord line and the aircraft's longitudinal axis. It's a fixed angle for wings, but variable for variable incidence tailplanes.",
    "id": "4cf574c6-01df-4a28-925f-5e4ecccf426a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the critical angle of attack?",
    "answer": "The angle between the chordline and the incoming airflow.",
    "id": "aa060ed0-a956-44e0-ba84-d114630db0a7"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the washout on a wing?",
    "answer": "A wing design feature where the angle of incidence of the wing decreases from the root to the tip.\n\nThis makes it so that the wing as a tendency to stall at the root first, maintaining aileron control for a longer time and providing a resistence to spinning, facilitating recovery.",
    "id": "d661dba7-698c-44e3-9981-c5de3567ce64"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is dihedral?",
    "answer": "Dihedral is the upward inclinitation of the wing from the root to the tip.",
    "id": "4d6bb2e2-2aa0-4f4a-817e-4aa7ac3cfea9"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is anhedral?",
    "answer": "anhedral is the downward inclinitation of the wing from the root to the tip.",
    "id": "2751588a-29b0-4348-a5f7-ee55cf5d2a2d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is lift?",
    "answer": "Lift is the component of the total aerodynamic force perpendicular to the relative airflow.\n\nLift is generated when a streamlined body, such as an aerofoil, is placed in a flow of air.",
    "id": "1b1088e2-dec1-4e57-8f06-60c5ece12a24"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is drag?",
    "answer": "Drag is the component of the total aerodynamic force parallel to the relative airflow.\n\nDrag is generated by any body placed in a flow and it's composed of friction, form, and pressure drag.",
    "id": "e66ceb56-3270-428f-974a-50df3672b56b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the formula for Lift?",
    "answer": "L = 1/2 * rho * Cl * A * V^2",
    "id": "39326f2a-44e4-4388-b610-48d4921d2f83"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the coefficient of Lift?",
    "answer": "An adymensional number relating the lift with the dynamic pressure of the incoming flow. It is dependent on the form of the object and the angle of attack.",
    "id": "c8f682a2-8bfb-4800-90f8-6c6511c1585e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the center of pressure?",
    "answer": "An aerofoil when placed in a flow will (normally) cause said flow to accelerate over the aerofoil and decelerate below it.\n\nThis will cause a pressure differential between the upper and lower surface of the aerofoil, and the resultant force will be applied at the **center of pressure**.",
    "id": "de51e843-958a-4685-86ef-91ad17a6204b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe the movement of the center of pressure with varying angle of attack.",
    "answer": "The Center of pressure position is dependent of the angle of attack. As the angle of attack increases the center of pressure moves closer to the leading edge.",
    "id": "2a9c94d8-a561-472f-a232-e9d185b0765f"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe the lift-weight pitching moments.",
    "answer": "The weight of an aircraft is applied at the CG. The lift at the CP. The relative position between these 2 points determines the stability of the aircraft. For an Aircraft with a tail surface, a CG in front of the CP constitutes a stable system, while a CG behind the CP an unstable system.",
    "id": "43a0913e-6a49-4edb-bb5c-1e40edc2da5b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe aspect ratio.",
    "answer": "The ratio between the wing span and the mean chord line.\n\nA high aspect ratio is associated with good lift to drag ratio, i.e.: Gliders.\n\n A low aspect ratio is usually associated with fast aircraft, i.e.: Fighter jets.",
    "id": "43a0913e-6a49-4edb-bb5c-1e403dc2da5b"
  },
  {
    "question": "During what phase of flight is lift the greatest?",
    "answer": "For a commerical aeroplane: During take off. At this point the aircraft has it it's maximum weight, and accelerating in the vertical plane requiring the highest ammount of lift to counteract the weight.",
    "id": "43a0x13e-6a49-4edb-bb5c-1e403dc2da5b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What systems protect against a stall?",
    "answer": "Stall warning, stick shaker, stick pusher, etc...\n\nGenerically we can destinguish between systems that alert the pilot of the impeding stall, like stall the stall warning or stick shaker, and systems that try to correct the situation, like a stick pusher.",
    "id": "43a0x13e-6a49-4edc-bb5c-1e403dc2da5b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Dutch roll?",
    "answer": "Dutch roll is an aircraft stability issue involving oscillations of rolling and yawing motions. It occurs when the aircraft's nose deviates from its path, causing rolling in the opposite direction due to the vertical fin's side force. This generates a yawing moment, resulting in a cycle of yawing and rolling motions. Dutch roll can be problematic for passenger comfort and pilot control. Measures like tail fin design, yaw dampers, and control inputs are used to counteract it and maintain stability.",
    "id": "43a0x13e-6a49-4edb-bb5c-1e4034c2da5b"
  }
]
